<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Gaming Blog of the Digital Jedi</title>
        <link>https://joeyg.me/RSSfeed_gaming.xml</link>
        <description>The documented gaming journey of an old school gamer and newbie retro game collector learning the ways of the Jedi</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 19:52:14 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I Got Into Video Game Collecting]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-got-into-vido-game-collecting</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-got-into-vido-game-collecting</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[The story of how I came to know video games as a kid, strayed from them as a teenager, and ultimately became a passionate collector and player as an adult.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[My Introduction to Video Games

I'm about to be 38 years old. Why am I telling you that? Well, I feel like it helps provide perspective into why collecting retro and even modern video games is so interesting to me. I won an NES in 1986 or 1987 (I'm not really sure which) from a little league baseball raffle. Basically, if you sold over 500 candy bars you got your name into a drawing for the NES and a copy of the game simply titled "Baseball". My dad was a driver for UPS and basically did all the work for me by selling the candy bars while he was on his route. Low and behold, they drew my name. Until that day I wasn't even aware of the NES and my only exposure to video games was playing my uncle's Atari 2600 while at my grandparent's house. Winning that NES changed my life forever!

I didn't fall in love with video games immediately though. I vaguely remember thinking the NES was really cool after I spent some time with it, but being that I was somewhere around 6 years old, my attention span was very short and I had many other interests. I can remember receiving a handful of games that Christmas from various family members and I'd be lying if I said I remembered exactly which ones I received. I do feel like that started my obsession though. Now I had options other than Super Mario Bros and Baseball! Still, my time with the NES was limited due to the fact that it was connected to the living room TV and my family had shows to watch at certain times and rented VHS tape that had to be viewed by a certain day before they were due back at the rental store. That too was soon to change.

The following year my grandparents and parents all chipped in to buy me a TV for my birthday. I didn't grow up as part of a family with lots of money and TVs seemed like a much bigger purchase back then than they do these days so it was a very big deal to have my own TV in my room. I'm not sure of the size, but if I had to guess I would say it was maybe a 19-inch screen. It had 2 knobs protruding from the wood grain on the right side; one for VHF channels and one for VHF channels. There was also a small switch to allow toggling between VHF and UHF. The rear of the TV simply had the 2 screws sticking our for you to connect various things. I remember my dad got me what was called an RF modulator to simplify the process of connecting things to the TV allowing for RCA and coaxial connections to be made much more easily. Now that I could play NES at any time without dealing with the schedules of my other family members, I began to become hooked!

I'll spare you the details of the next few years, but in summation, I kept acquiring new games through various methods and my love for video games continued to flourish. My dad would sometimes say things like "If you score a goal today at your soccer game, I'll buy you a new game." My mom would approach things a bit differently setting goals such as "If you have straight A's on this report card we can go buy another NES game." Regardless, I was motivated and it really helped that I was a good student. I can't honestly say that I earned a ton of games through the sports-related goals my dad would set for me, but I only made a couple of B's the entirety of going to school so I got a lot of games that way. When I had friends over, we played NES games. When the weekend hit and the weather wasn't nice enough to play outside, I locked myself into my bedroom and played more video games. As my love grew, so did my collection of games.

From Casual Gamer to Obsessed

There came a point around the age of 9 or 10 where two very important things happened; my uncle gave me an Apple IIC and I got a Sega Genesis. The Apple was a big deal because it came with a large plastic container full of 5.25" disks, most of which were games. It also came with a stack of magazines that each had the BASIC code for at least 1 game. I remember sitting in front of that computer on the weekend for what seemed like hours; meticulously typing each numbered line of code, saving the game to a blank disc, then crossing my fingers as I tried to run the game. This was my introduction to writing code as I later started to gain a basic understanding of what I was typing and began making changes to the code. This was also another platform for which I could play video games. Meanwhile, the Genesis collection started to grow through the usual means and slowly began to win my affection over my NES.

At some point, I got a GameBoy. It was always a second class citizen to me as I much preferred a home console over a tiny, pea green screen. The GameBoy got me through some road trips and long stints in waiting rooms though and for that, I very much appreciated having it.

The "Dark" Period

Things didn't really change for a few years. I kept acquiring games, kept inviting friends over to play them with me, and continued to view video games as one of the great things in life. Then high school hit and suddenly I was more interested in playing guitar and girls. Video games began to take a back seat except for the random times I was at a friend's house and we would throw down on some GoldenEye or Micro Machines on the N64. The Genesis remained the last video game console of my childhood. I still liked playing video games, I was just starting to care a little less about them.

It was probably my senior year when I decided that selling my entire collection of video games was a good idea. My parents were having a garage sale and told my sister and me that if we put things in the sale we could keep the money we made. I needed money for dates, gas was up to $.98 a gallon at the time which had me irate, and $4.75 per hour stocking shelves at the local grocery store wasn't allowing me to spend money the way I wanted. I got rid of it all!

The Rebirth of the Gamer Within

Fast forward to my stint at college and my unofficial roommate (basically a good friend that crashed on the couch for free) had a Sony PlayStation. My actual roommate had a Sega Master System. When we weren't partying or didn't feel like going to class, these systems got used heavily. I beat Final Fantasy VII during this period and gained an appreciation for the Master System and its library. Still, I didn't own any video games.

A few years later I moved to Austin, TX with what is now my wife to further pursue my music career. I had joined a metal band while in college and we quickly began to feel like we had outgrown our hometown area and needed to move to a bigger market to hopefully "make it" in the music biz. My mother bought my wife a Nintendo GameCube which was sort of my doing. I might have told my mom that was a good idea. My thought process was that by getting a GameCube I could maybe get my wife into video games and, at the same time, I would FINALLY have a video game system under my own roof again! I wanted to play video games again and I wanted my wife to love video games as much as I did. She did eventually gain love and respect for video games, but it is nowhere near the love and respect I possess. I also managed to convince my mom to give me her old PS2 around this time. She bought it to be used as a DVD player and standalone DVD players had come down quite a bit at this point. Finally, I was acquiring video games again!

Years passed and video games slowly became a bigger part of my life. I would friends over to play Guitar Hero and have some drinks, I would periodically grab a handful of old games to take to GameStop and trade in for a new game or two, and I regularly found myself killing times playing video games again. It was nice. I got into video games enough that I had to have a PS3 near launch. A coworker had a PSP for sale and I jumped on it. Slowly my collection was growing, but I still didn't view it as collecting. I was merely enjoying video games as much as I could.

Kids Change Everything

When I found out my wife was pregnant I knew that the habit of buying videos games regularly was about to come to an end. I did immediately have the thought "I can't wait until the kiddo is old enough to play video games with me!" I didn't really get a lot of new games or consoles the first few years of parenthood. I did, at one point, happen into a lucky deal with a coworker of my wife's that had an old NES in PERFECT condition and 18 games they wanted to unload for a whopping $100. I didn't even hesitate to grab that up!

Once my son was about 4, we decided to get a Wii. They had been out for a few years already so I got a used on one the cheap and introduced my son to video games. The simplicity of some of the Wii games really made it easy for my kiddo to enjoy playing them. Suddenly playing video games was a family activity that we all seemed to enjoy. This led to the decision to buy a Wii U as a Christmas gift for the household a couple of years later.

My collection kept growing as I was no longer selling off games or trading them in for new ones. I had a handful of PS2 and GameCube games that survived several moves too. Once I got my first "good paying" developer job, my amazing wife decided it was time for me to have a current-gen console and got me the PS4 Pro for Christmas the year that the Pro model was released. My love for video games was now shared with my wife and son and we regularly played games together.

From "Gamer" to "Collector"

Finally, a couple of years ago, I started to feel a deep nostalgia for the older games and consoles. I was not only interested in getting an NES and a Genesis like I had growing up, but I started to think about the consoles I completely missed out on such as the Sega Saturn, Sega Dreamcast, and more. I occasionally found myself on eBay picking up a new console or game. Then we discovered a local retro games shops called Game Over Videogames. Before we knew it, we were taking at least a couple of trips a month to GameOver to pick up something new-to-us.

This was the point I decided I wanted to be a "collector". I enjoyed tracking down old games and consoles, trying to find the best deal, repairing these old items to work like new once again, and ultimately, playing these older games. I was hooked! It occurred to me that real collectors don't pay retail so I started looking for good eBay lots, going to flea markets, and scouring Craiglist to find the best deals possible. Over the past 2 years I've gained about 250 more games and my console collection now totals 26. My love for collecting continues to grow stronger as the size of my collection swells. My son has even started a collection of his own now and probably has to be one of the only 10 years olds around that asked for a PS2 of his own even though he already has his own Switch, 3DS, and gaming PC. We're now a family of gamers and I've become a passionate collector over the years. It was a long journey for me to get to this point, but now I'm excited about the years of collecting ahead of me!
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Connecting All of Those Consoles]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/the-struggle-of-hookinh-it-all-up</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/the-struggle-of-hookinh-it-all-up</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[An overview of how I keep all of my consoles connected to my 4K TV for the best picture possible on a budget.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[A Gamer as Well as a Collector

Collecting video games, old and new, is a passion of mine. Aside from just collecting game, I've also been playing video games for about 32 years and I don't plan on stopping! Considering that modern televisions usually only come with a few HDMI inputs and nothing else, connecting a bunch of consoles (especially the old ones) can prove to be challenging. Here's an overview of how I did this on a budget and what I plan on doing to continue to improve my setup.

Cheap Upscalers are Good for a Start

Back in the days of old, those of us in North America connected things to our televisions using the old composite/RCA cables. If you go far enough back in time you would find yourself connecting something to a TV using a coaxial cable or even one of those old balun connectors that required you to use a screwdriver to make sure the connection stayed in place. There was a brief period where console manufacturers were releasing S-Video cables, but I'm not sure if very many people were using them. Component cables came around a little later, but even now you would be hard pressed to find a new TV with component connections. So how do you hook up your old consoles to modern TVs? One word: upscalers.

Upscalers come in many forms for many different types of connections and the range in price point is drastic. For the beginning collector or even the budget-minded enthusiast, there are many options out there though. The easiest way to get your old NES or Genesis connected to your TV for the least amount of money involves purchasing a composite to HDMI upscaler from a retailer like Amazon. You can usually find them for around $35-$40 and they really couldn't be easier to connect. Now I'm not going to lie, they are cheaply made (usually in China), they don't do the best job in the world of upscaling the picture, they add a little bit of input lag, and they usually stretch the picture to fill the whole screen instead of maintaining the original aspect ratio. Still, if you're on a budget or in a hurry, this is the simplest route to go and the result is "good enough". Just read the reviews to make sure you're not getting a product that is total garbage. Here's a link to one that I've had success with: Tendak 3RCA AV CVBS Composite &amp; S-Video R/L Audio to HDMI Converter Adapter

So What is an Upscaler?

Upscalers do 2 things: they enlarge the video signal to the desired size and they allow you to convert a connection type to another type. Old consoles like the NES and Sega Genesis output in 240p meaning that the picture is 240 pixels tall and drawn on your screen progressively. Later consoles like the GameCube were still only 480i. If you have a regular HD TV then it can handle 1080p or 1080 pixels high. There's a bit of a gap there, and an upscaler uses various methods to fill that gap. Usually, it just doubles, triples, or quadruples the amount of pixels being drawn. This is necessary because TV manufacturers don't care about how a new TV handles a signal from an older device like your NES so they don't add quality upscaling to their TV sets. This results in very poor picture quality and, in some cases, it can even mean you won't see a picture at all.

Now that you know that you need an upscaler to connect your old consoles to your new TV and have a basic understanding of what they do, it is worth knowing that there are some high-end upscalers out there that will give you mind-boggling results. Be prepared to shell out some cash for them though! Usually, these upscalers come loaded with several connection and software options allowing you to customize your experience to suit your needs and they don't introduce any input lag.

Easily the most coveted upscaler out there is the Micomsoft Framemeister. Not only will this thing allow you to connect to it with several different connection types, but it also has a wireless remote that allows you to set various options including some filters that can sharpen or smooth out your picture. You won't find these in stores, but you can commonly find them on eBay if you want to get the best instead of messing with the rest. Just be prepared to shell out between $400-$450 or more (at least at the time this was written).

Thankfully there have been other high-end alternatives coming to the market over recent years. The most recent one that has gotten my attention is the RetroTINK. For about $100 you get a small little powerhouse that can accept you s-video, component, and composite connections and do a superb job of converting them to 480p picture through an HDMI cable. Now obviously 480p still isn't HD, but MOST modern TVs will do a pretty nice job handling a signal at least that resolution. Likewise, for about double the price, you can look for an OSSC which can get you up to 720p output in some cases and has a slew of options for your endless tinkering!

A Word About Cables

Can you just grab the right upscaler, plug in the original cable from your console, plug the HDMI output into your TV, and go to town on some retro games? Sure, but if you're anything like me you'll want the best picture possible and your original cables are not the best option. This is where things can get pretty deeply confusing, so I'll just touch on the basics here.

As far as HDMI cables are concerned, buy the cheapest ones you can find! Those $100+ Monster cables are a complete rip off! Basically, if it is an analog cable then those pricey, super shielded cables with gold plated connectors are actually the best route to go. Analog signals pick up interference and can get weaker the farther they travel so quality cables are needed. HDMI cables pass a digital signal that is not prone to interference, therefore, those super fat, shielded cables you see at Best Buy are nothing more than a marketing scam that preys on the less informed. You are no longer in the "less informed" group!

All that said, your older consoles DO output an analog signal so quality cables are a must. What complicates things even more is the fact that most older consoles are also capable of outputting over different cable types than what most of us are used to using. For example, if you had a Sega Genesis as a kid and you lived in North America then you probably connected it to your television using the standard yellow composite cable. I currently have my Genesis connected to an upscaler using a European SCART cable and no modification was required. So what does that matter? Well, the old composite cable is really the worst possible option out there because it passes all color and brightness data over 1 connection allowing the signal to more or less interfere with itself. This results in a fuzzy picture with terrible colors. Did you ever wonder why the sky in Super Mario Bros was purple? It isn't! Your crappy composite cable output it that way. It really is blue if you output RGB. Different consoles have different sets of cable types they can use in their stock, non-modded form. If you want to get the best cable possible for your console, just Google something like "best cable for connecting a " or "does a  output RGB with SCART". Basically, I try to get everything to output through RGB via SCART or component if possible, but some consoles like the NES or N64 won't do this without modification so research is key here.

Modified Consoles

If you're into retro gaming and have never explored the world of modified consoles, you have no idea what you are missing! The purist in me appreciates an old game console in its original state and, if I buy a modified console, I make sure I always have an unmodified version of that console first for the sake of collecting. You can get a modified NES that outputs RGB resulting in an amazing upscaled picture. I even have a modified N64 from Japan that not only plays US and Japanese games, but it also outputs pure RGB and has the "de-blur" mod which sharpens the pixels even more! You can find some really insane modifications to most of the older consoles if you look around a little bit, especially on eBay. Just beware, there are sellers out there that do some pretty poor quality work. Make sure to check seller ratings and do your homework before buying a hardware modified console. I even recommend checking out folks like Voultar who do outstanding work and can either mod your console for you or sell you one that is already modded. If you have some pretty solid soldering skills then you can buy mod-kits and do the modifications yourself which will save a load of cash!

Switchers

As your collection grows, you might find that you have more than 1 console with a certain connection type and most upscalers only accept 1 connection. What to do? Well, there is also a world of switchers out there. Just like with the upscalers, you will find that switchers range in price and performance as well, although the difference isn't quite as big a deal as it is with the upscalers. Currently, I have switchers for SCART, component, s-video, and even composite connections. This allows me to connect multiple consoles to the switcher then connect that into the upscaler. Buying the pricier switchers can result in a SLIGHTLY better picture as the switcher itself won't negatively affect the signal. Still, the cheap ones do the job in a pinch.

What Do I Do With All These HDMI Cables?

So you've acquired some consoles, purchased the desired cables for the job, connected everything to the required switcher, got upscalers to turn everything into HDMI, and now the number of HDMI connections on your TV falls WAY short fo what you need. Not a problem! They make switchers for those as well and they are pretty cheap. Amazon is a good resource for buying these and there is no need to spend more money than you have to unless you just want one with more ports. An example of this is where I recently spent $100 on a Monoprice 8-port HDMI switcher because I was tired of having so many 4-port switchers sitting on my TV stand. I bought that just to clean up the mess a bit.

Another thing to keep in mind is that if you have a surround receiver, it is likely to have a handful of HDMI connections on the back. In my case, I used up the 3 on the back of my surround receiver and 4 on the back of my TV before I ever purchased an HDMI switcher. Use this approach to avoid spending more than you have to until you have to!

The Details

It goes without saying that you are going to have to power all of your consoles. Be prepared to sink some money into buying power strips. I suggest you make sure to buy the ones with extra space between the outlets because most old consoles have those huge wall wart power connectors and half or more of the outlets on a normal power strip will go to waste due to the fact that these wall warts will overlap 2 or 3 other outlets. Optionally, you can invest in a power conditioner which not only gives you many more outlets, but it also cleans the power signal and is better capable of handling surges. These can get pretty expensive, but if you have some more collectible/more expensive consoles then they are worth the expense. I have one and it powers the best of my collection where all of the others are plugged into regular power strips.

Aside from that you'll probably want some sort of cable management solution. I just use velcro straps to bundle together large masses of cables, but admittedly I'm not the best person to tell you how to handle cable management as mine are a mess! There are other solutions out there and this is an area where you can get creative with your solution.

Hopefully you now have a basic understanding of how to connect a bunch of old consoles to a modern television (or at least how I do it). Having a bunch of consoles connected at once can be rewarding and always sparks up a conversation with guests. It's nice to be able to power on a switch and a console, drop in a game, and just start playing immediately. Don't just collect em all, play em all too!
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>