<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Gaming Blog of the Digital Jedi</title>
        <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming</link>
        <description>The documented gaming journey of an old school gamer and newbie retro game collector learning the ways of the Jedi</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 23:39:17 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <category>Video Games</category>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I Got Into Video Game Collecting]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-got-into-vido-game-collecting</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-got-into-vido-game-collecting</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The story of how I came to know video games as a kid, strayed from them as a teenager, and ultimately became a passionate collector and player as an adult.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="my-introduction-to-video-games">My Introduction to Video Games</h2>
<p>I’m about to be 38 years old. Why am I telling you that? Well, I feel like it helps provide perspective into why collecting retro and even modern video games is so interesting to me. I won an NES in 1986 or 1987 (I’m not really sure which) from a little league baseball raffle. Basically, if you sold over 500 candy bars you got your name into a drawing for the NES and a copy of the game simply titled “Baseball”. My dad was a driver for UPS and basically did all the work for me by selling the candy bars while he was on his route. Low and behold, they drew my name. Until that day I wasn’t even aware of the NES and my only exposure to video games was playing my uncle’s Atari 2600 while at my grandparent’s house. Winning that NES changed my life forever!</p>
<p>I didn’t fall in love with video games immediately though. I vaguely remember thinking the NES was really cool after I spent some time with it, but being that I was somewhere around 6 years old, my attention span was very short and I had many other interests. I can remember receiving a handful of games that Christmas from various family members and I’d be lying if I said I remembered exactly which ones I received. I do feel like that started my obsession though. Now I had options other than Super Mario Bros and Baseball! Still, my time with the NES was limited due to the fact that it was connected to the living room TV and my family had shows to watch at certain times and rented VHS tape that had to be viewed by a certain day before they were due back at the rental store. That too was soon to change.</p>
<p>The following year my grandparents and parents all chipped in to buy me a TV for my birthday. I didn’t grow up as part of a family with lots of money and TVs seemed like a much bigger purchase back then than they do these days so it was a very big deal to have my own TV in my room. I’m not sure of the size, but if I had to guess I would say it was maybe a 19-inch screen. It had 2 knobs protruding from the wood grain on the right side; one for VHF channels and one for VHF channels. There was also a small switch to allow toggling between VHF and UHF. The rear of the TV simply had the 2 screws sticking our for you to connect various things. I remember my dad got me what was called an RF modulator to simplify the process of connecting things to the TV allowing for RCA and coaxial connections to be made much more easily. Now that I could play NES at any time without dealing with the schedules of my other family members, I began to become hooked!</p>
<p>I’ll spare you the details of the next few years, but in summation, I kept acquiring new games through various methods and my love for video games continued to flourish. My dad would sometimes say things like “If you score a goal today at your soccer game, I’ll buy you a new game.” My mom would approach things a bit differently setting goals such as “If you have straight A’s on this report card we can go buy another NES game.” Regardless, I was motivated and it really helped that I was a good student. I can’t honestly say that I earned a ton of games through the sports-related goals my dad would set for me, but I only made a couple of B’s the entirety of going to school so I got a lot of games that way. When I had friends over, we played NES games. When the weekend hit and the weather wasn’t nice enough to play outside, I locked myself into my bedroom and played more video games. As my love grew, so did my collection of games.</p>
<h2 id="from-casual-gamer-to-obsessed">From Casual Gamer to Obsessed</h2>
<p>There came a point around the age of 9 or 10 where two very important things happened; my uncle gave me an Apple IIC and I got a Sega Genesis. The Apple was a big deal because it came with a large plastic container full of 5.25” disks, most of which were games. It also came with a stack of magazines that each had the BASIC code for at least 1 game. I remember sitting in front of that computer on the weekend for what seemed like hours; meticulously typing each numbered line of code, saving the game to a blank disc, then crossing my fingers as I tried to run the game. This was my introduction to writing code as I later started to gain a basic understanding of what I was typing and began making changes to the code. This was also another platform for which I could play video games. Meanwhile, the Genesis collection started to grow through the usual means and slowly began to win my affection over my NES.</p>
<p>At some point, I got a GameBoy. It was always a second class citizen to me as I much preferred a home console over a tiny, pea green screen. The GameBoy got me through some road trips and long stints in waiting rooms though and for that, I very much appreciated having it.</p>
<h2 id="the-dark-period">The “Dark” Period</h2>
<p>Things didn’t really change for a few years. I kept acquiring games, kept inviting friends over to play them with me, and continued to view video games as one of the great things in life. Then high school hit and suddenly I was more interested in playing guitar and girls. Video games began to take a back seat except for the random times I was at a friend’s house and we would throw down on some GoldenEye or Micro Machines on the N64. The Genesis remained the last video game console of my childhood. I still liked playing video games, I was just starting to care a little less about them.</p>
<p>It was probably my senior year when I decided that selling my entire collection of video games was a good idea. My parents were having a garage sale and told my sister and me that if we put things in the sale we could keep the money we made. I needed money for dates, gas was up to $.98 a gallon at the time which had me irate, and $4.75 per hour stocking shelves at the local grocery store wasn’t allowing me to spend money the way I wanted. I got rid of it all!</p>
<h2 id="the-rebirth-of-the-gamer-within">The Rebirth of the Gamer Within</h2>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515486/gaming/RGB_deblurred_N64.jpg" alt="Japanese teal N64 region modded and RGB modded"  onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515486/gaming/RGB_deblurred_N64.jpg')">
</div>

<p>Fast forward to my stint at college and my unofficial roommate (basically a good friend that crashed on the couch for free) had a Sony PlayStation. My actual roommate had a Sega Master System. When we weren’t partying or didn’t feel like going to class, these systems got used heavily. I beat Final Fantasy VII during this period and gained an appreciation for the Master System and its library. Still, I didn’t own any video games.</p>
<p>A few years later I moved to Austin, TX with what is now my wife to further pursue my music career. I had joined a metal band while in college and we quickly began to feel like we had outgrown our hometown area and needed to move to a bigger market to hopefully “make it” in the music biz. My mother bought my wife a Nintendo GameCube which was sort of my doing. I might have told my mom that was a good idea. My thought process was that by getting a GameCube I could maybe get my wife into video games and, at the same time, I would FINALLY have a video game system under my own roof again! I wanted to play video games again and I wanted my wife to love video games as much as I did. She did eventually gain love and respect for video games, but it is nowhere near the love and respect I possess. I also managed to convince my mom to give me her old PS2 around this time. She bought it to be used as a DVD player and standalone DVD players had come down quite a bit at this point. Finally, I was acquiring video games again!</p>
<p>Years passed and video games slowly became a bigger part of my life. I would friends over to play Guitar Hero and have some drinks, I would periodically grab a handful of old games to take to GameStop and trade in for a new game or two, and I regularly found myself killing times playing video games again. It was nice. I got into video games enough that I had to have a PS3 near launch. A coworker had a PSP for sale and I jumped on it. Slowly my collection was growing, but I still didn’t view it as collecting. I was merely enjoying video games as much as I could.</p>
<h2 id="kids-change-everything">Kids Change Everything</h2>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/early_collection.jpg" alt="early image of Joey Gauthier's game collection" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/early_collection.jpg')">
</div>

<p>When I found out my wife was pregnant I knew that the habit of buying videos games regularly was about to come to an end. I did immediately have the thought “I can’t wait until the kiddo is old enough to play video games with me!” I didn’t really get a lot of new games or consoles the first few years of parenthood. I did, at one point, happen into a lucky deal with a coworker of my wife’s that had an old NES in PERFECT condition and 18 games they wanted to unload for a whopping $100. I didn’t even hesitate to grab that up!</p>
<p>Once my son was about 4, we decided to get a Wii. They had been out for a few years already so I got a used on one the cheap and introduced my son to video games. The simplicity of some of the Wii games really made it easy for my kiddo to enjoy playing them. Suddenly playing video games was a family activity that we all seemed to enjoy. This led to the decision to buy a Wii U as a Christmas gift for the household a couple of years later.</p>
<p>My collection kept growing as I was no longer selling off games or trading them in for new ones. I had a handful of PS2 and GameCube games that survived several moves too. Once I got my first “good paying” developer job, my amazing wife decided it was time for me to have a current-gen console and got me the PS4 Pro for Christmas the year that the Pro model was released. My love for video games was now shared with my wife and son and we regularly played games together.</p>
<h2 id="from-gamer-to-collector">From “Gamer” to “Collector”</h2>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/march_2019_collection.jpg" alt="image of Joey Gauthier's retro game collection circa March 2019" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/march_2019_collection.jpg')">
</div>

<p>Finally, a couple of years ago, I started to feel a deep nostalgia for the older games and consoles. I was not only interested in getting an NES and a Genesis like I had growing up, but I started to think about the consoles I completely missed out on such as the Sega Saturn, Sega Dreamcast, and more. I occasionally found myself on eBay picking up a new console or game. Then we discovered a local retro games shops called <a href="https://gameovervideogames.com/">Game Over Videogames</a>. Before we knew it, we were taking at least a couple of trips a month to GameOver to pick up something new-to-us.</p>
<p>This was the point I decided I wanted to be a “collector”. I enjoyed tracking down old games and consoles, trying to find the best deal, repairing these old items to work like new once again, and ultimately, playing these older games. I was hooked! It occurred to me that real collectors don’t pay retail so I started looking for good eBay lots, going to flea markets, and scouring Craiglist to find the best deals possible. Over the past 2 years I’ve gained about 250 more games and my console collection now totals 26. My love for collecting continues to grow stronger as the size of my collection swells. My son has even started a collection of his own now and probably has to be one of the only 10 years olds around that asked for a PS2 of his own even though he already has his own Switch, 3DS, and gaming PC. We’re now a family of gamers and I’ve become a passionate collector over the years. It was a long journey for me to get to this point, but now I’m excited about the years of collecting ahead of me!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Connecting All of Those Consoles]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/the-struggle-of-hookinh-it-all-up</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/the-struggle-of-hookinh-it-all-up</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[An overview of how I keep all of my consoles connected to my 4K TV for the best picture possible on a budget.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-gamer-as-well-as-a-collector">A Gamer as Well as a Collector</h2>
<p>Collecting video games, old and new, is a passion of mine. Aside from just collecting game, I’ve also been playing video games for about 32 years and I don’t plan on stopping! Considering that modern televisions usually only come with a few HDMI inputs and nothing else, connecting a bunch of consoles (especially the old ones) can prove to be challenging. Here’s an overview of how I did this on a budget and what I plan on doing to continue to improve my setup.</p>
<h2 id="cheap-upscalers-are-good-for-a-start">Cheap Upscalers are Good for a Start</h2>
<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00V2ULHBS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B00V2ULHBS&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=c88389c43755e3247e3f7378cfd1d110">
    <div class="image-container">
        <img border="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=US&ASIN=B00V2ULHBS&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=joeyg0e-20" >
    </div>
</a><img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B00V2ULHBS" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />

<p>Back in the days of old, those of us in North America connected things to our televisions using the old composite/RCA cables. If you go far enough back in time you would find yourself connecting something to a TV using a coaxial cable or even one of those old balun connectors that required you to use a screwdriver to make sure the connection stayed in place. There was a brief period where console manufacturers were releasing S-Video cables, but I’m not sure if very many people were using them. Component cables came around a little later, but even now you would be hard pressed to find a new TV with component connections. So how do you hook up your old consoles to modern TVs? One word: upscalers.</p>
<p>Upscalers come in many forms for many different types of connections and the range in price point is drastic. For the beginning collector or even the budget-minded enthusiast, there are many options out there though. The easiest way to get your old NES or Genesis connected to your TV for the least amount of money involves purchasing a composite to HDMI upscaler from a retailer like Amazon. You can usually find them for around $35-$40 and they really couldn’t be easier to connect. Now I’m not going to lie, they are cheaply made (usually in China), they don’t do the best job in the world of upscaling the picture, they add a little bit of input lag, and they usually stretch the picture to fill the whole screen instead of maintaining the original aspect ratio. Still, if you’re on a budget or in a hurry, this is the simplest route to go and the result is “good enough”. Just read the reviews to make sure you’re not getting a product that is total garbage. Here’s a link to one that I’ve had success with: <a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00V2ULHBS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B00V2ULHBS&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=d1232d3320a1fe6d3e3ee1fc8ed2ecd5">Tendak 3RCA AV CVBS Composite &amp; S-Video R/L Audio to HDMI Converter Adapter</a><img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B00V2ULHBS" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /></p>
<h2 id="so-what-is-an-upscaler">So What is an Upscaler?</h2>
<p>Upscalers do 2 things: they enlarge the video signal to the desired size and they allow you to convert a connection type to another type. Old consoles like the NES and Sega Genesis output in 240p meaning that the picture is 240 pixels tall and drawn on your screen progressively. Later consoles like the GameCube were still only 480i. If you have a regular HD TV then it can handle 1080p or 1080 pixels high. There’s a bit of a gap there, and an upscaler uses various methods to fill that gap. Usually, it just doubles, triples, or quadruples the amount of pixels being drawn. This is necessary because TV manufacturers don’t care about how a new TV handles a signal from an older device like your NES so they don’t add quality upscaling to their TV sets. This results in very poor picture quality and, in some cases, it can even mean you won’t see a picture at all.</p>
<p>Now that you know that you need an upscaler to connect your old consoles to your new TV and have a basic understanding of what they do, it is worth knowing that there are some high-end upscalers out there that will give you mind-boggling results. Be prepared to shell out some cash for them though! Usually, these upscalers come loaded with several connection and software options allowing you to customize your experience to suit your needs and they don’t introduce any input lag.</p>
<p>Easily the most coveted upscaler out there is the Micomsoft Framemeister. Not only will this thing allow you to connect to it with several different connection types, but it also has a wireless remote that allows you to set various options including some filters that can sharpen or smooth out your picture. You won’t find these in stores, but you can commonly find them on eBay if you want to get the best instead of messing with the rest. Just be prepared to shell out between $400-$450 or more (at least at the time this was written).</p>
<p>Thankfully there have been other high-end alternatives coming to the market over recent years. The most recent one that has gotten my attention is the <a href="http://www.retrotink.com/">RetroTINK</a>. For about $100 you get a small little powerhouse that can accept you s-video, component, and composite connections and do a superb job of converting them to 480p picture through an HDMI cable. Now obviously 480p still isn’t HD, but MOST modern TVs will do a pretty nice job handling a signal at least that resolution. Likewise, for about double the price, you can look for an <a href="http://junkerhq.net/xrgb/index.php?title=OSSC">OSSC</a> which can get you up to 720p output in some cases and has a slew of options for your endless tinkering!</p>
<h2 id="a-word-about-cables">A Word About Cables</h2>
<p>Can you just grab the right upscaler, plug in the original cable from your console, plug the HDMI output into your TV, and go to town on some retro games? Sure, but if you’re anything like me you’ll want the best picture possible and your original cables are not the best option. This is where things can get pretty deeply confusing, so I’ll just touch on the basics here.</p>
<p>As far as HDMI cables are concerned, buy the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B014I8SX4Y/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B014I8SX4Y&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=014dffd24d786a50dc5bf6f8df0c6a2e" target="__blank">cheapest ones you can find!</a> Those $100+ Monster cables are a complete rip off! Basically, if it is an analog cable then those pricey, super shielded cables with gold plated connectors are actually the best route to go. Analog signals pick up interference and can get weaker the farther they travel so quality cables are needed. HDMI cables pass a digital signal that is not prone to interference, therefore, those super fat, shielded cables you see at Best Buy are nothing more than a marketing scam that preys on the less informed. You are no longer in the “less informed” group!</p>
<p>All that said, your older consoles DO output an analog signal so quality cables are a must. What complicates things even more is the fact that most older consoles are also capable of outputting over different cable types than what most of us are used to using. For example, if you had a Sega Genesis as a kid and you lived in North America then you probably connected it to your television using the standard yellow composite cable. I currently have my Genesis connected to an upscaler using a <a target="__blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07KWH32WS/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B07KWH32WS&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=dd8705d59256767d573591c364d80858">European SCART cable</a> and no modification was required. So what does that matter? Well, the old composite cable is really the worst possible option out there because it passes all color and brightness data over 1 connection allowing the signal to more or less interfere with itself. This results in a fuzzy picture with terrible colors. Did you ever wonder why the sky in Super Mario Bros was purple? It isn’t! Your crappy composite cable output it that way. It really is blue if you output RGB. Different consoles have different sets of cable types they can use in their stock, non-modded form. If you want to get the best cable possible for your console, just Google something like “best cable for connecting a &lt;-your console here-&gt;” or “does a &lt;-your console here-&gt; output RGB with SCART”. Basically, I try to get everything to output through RGB via SCART or component if possible, but some consoles like the NES or N64 won’t do this without modification so research is key here.</p>
<h2 id="modified-consoles">Modified Consoles</h2>
<p>If you’re into retro gaming and have never explored the world of modified consoles, you have no idea what you are missing! The purist in me appreciates an old game console in its original state and, if I buy a modified console, I make sure I always have an unmodified version of that console first for the sake of collecting. You can get a modified NES that outputs RGB resulting in an amazing upscaled picture. I even have a modified N64 from Japan that not only plays US and Japanese games, but it also outputs pure RGB and has the “de-blur” mod which sharpens the pixels even more! You can find some really insane modifications to most of the older consoles if you look around a little bit, especially on eBay. Just beware, there are sellers out there that do some pretty poor quality work. Make sure to check seller ratings and do your homework before buying a hardware modified console. I even recommend checking out folks like <a href="https://voultar.com/index.php?route=common/home">Voultar</a> who do outstanding work and can either mod your console for you or sell you one that is already modded. If you have some pretty solid soldering skills then you can buy mod-kits and do the modifications yourself which will save a load of cash!</p>
<h2 id="switchers">Switchers</h2>
<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B07B9GHHH3/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B07B9GHHH3&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=fbfeafe413c79a74b766c2db36561690">
    <div class="image-container">
        <img border="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=US&ASIN=B07B9GHHH3&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=joeyg0e-20" >
        <img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B07B9GHHH3" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />
    </div>
</a>

<p>As your collection grows, you might find that you have more than 1 console with a certain connection type and most upscalers only accept 1 connection. What to do? Well, there is also a world of switchers out there. Just like with the upscalers, you will find that switchers range in price and performance as well, although the difference isn’t quite as big a deal as it is with the upscalers. Currently, I have switchers for SCART, component, s-video, and even composite connections. This allows me to connect multiple consoles to the switcher then connect that into the upscaler. Buying the pricier switchers can result in a SLIGHTLY better picture as the switcher itself won’t negatively affect the signal. Still, the cheap ones do the job in a pinch.</p>
<h2 id="what-do-i-do-with-all-these-hdmi-cables">What Do I Do With All These HDMI Cables?</h2>
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003L14X3A/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B003L14X3A&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=dd6389bfebd3cfc43677e443406e9533" target="__blank">
    <div class="image-container">
      <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515484/gaming/hdmi_switch.jpg" alt="Monoprice 8 port HDMI switch">
    </div>
</a>

<p>So you’ve acquired some consoles, purchased the desired cables for the job, connected everything to the required switcher, got upscalers to turn everything into HDMI, and now the number of HDMI connections on your TV falls WAY short fo what you need. Not a problem! They make switchers for those as well and they are pretty cheap. Amazon is a good resource for buying these and there is no need to spend more money than you have to unless you just want one with more ports. An example of this is where I recently spent $100 on a <a target="__blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003L14X3A/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B003L14X3A&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=dd6389bfebd3cfc43677e443406e9533">Monoprice 8-port HDMI switcher</a> because I was tired of having so many 4-port switchers sitting on my TV stand. I bought that just to clean up the mess a bit.</p>
<p>Another thing to keep in mind is that if you have a surround receiver, it is likely to have a handful of HDMI connections on the back. In my case, I used up the 3 on the back of my surround receiver and 4 on the back of my TV before I ever purchased an HDMI switcher. Use this approach to avoid spending more than you have to until you have to!</p>
<h2 id="the-details">The Details</h2>
<p>It goes without saying that you are going to have to power all of your consoles. Be prepared to sink some money into buying power strips. I suggest you make sure to buy the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01FHNBKYO/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B01FHNBKYO&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=51cde99afe71832ba99e12eca6e557a2" target="__blank">ones with extra space between the outlets</a> because most old consoles have those huge wall wart power connectors and half or more of the outlets on a normal power strip will go to waste due to the fact that these wall warts will overlap 2 or 3 other outlets. Optionally, you can invest in a power conditioner which not only gives you many more outlets, but it also cleans the power signal and is better capable of handling surges. These can get pretty expensive, but if you have some more collectible/more expensive consoles then they are worth the expense. I have one and it powers the best of my collection where all of the others are plugged into regular power strips.</p>
<div class="image-container">
     <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515483/gaming/cable_mess.jpg" alt="image of messy cables and power strips" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515483/gaming/cable_mess.jpg')">
</div>

<p>Aside from that you’ll probably want some sort of cable management solution. I just use velcro straps to bundle together large masses of cables, but admittedly I’m not the best person to tell you how to handle cable management as mine are a mess! There are other solutions out there and this is an area where you can get creative with your solution.</p>
<p>Hopefully you now have a basic understanding of how to connect a bunch of old consoles to a modern television (or at least how I do it). Having a bunch of consoles connected at once can be rewarding and always sparks up a conversation with guests. It’s nice to be able to power on a switch and a console, drop in a game, and just start playing immediately. Don’t just collect em all, play em all too!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I Add to My Collection]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-add-to-my-collection</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-add-to-my-collection</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Finding good deals on retro gaming items can be tricky! This is a high-level look at how I approach things.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You thought the above was the title? No, I’m asking where to get good deals! In all seriousness, I’ll go over some of the ways I acquire new games and game paraphernalia in this post, but I’ll also admit that I’m still trying to find new ways to get deals so feel free to comment and give me some more wisdom!</p>
<h2 id="sometimes-you-gotta-get-dirty">Sometimes You Gotta Get Dirty</h2>
<div class="image-container">
     <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515483/gaming/flea-market.jpg" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515483/gaming/flea-market.jpg')" alt="image of cluttered tables at a flea market">
</div>

<p>One of the most obvious things you can do to find deals is to be going to garage sales, flea markets, and all other forms of shady places where you might find someone selling video games regularly. I’ve looked in my area and, unfortunately, there aren’t a lot of flea markets worth visiting. There is one, and it is actually quite close, but the sellers there sometimes have ridiculous ideas about what they should ask for their games. On my last visit, I grabbed 5 PS2 games at a booth for $20. Not great, but not too bad either. About 15 minutes later I grabbed Killzone 1-3 for the PS3 at another booth and asked the guy how much he wanted. He replied with $20. I sat them down and continued walking. $6.33 per game isn’t terrible, but from a shady seller at a flea market, that is a price that I will pass up.</p>
<p>Garage sales are a bit easier to deal with these days thanks to the wonderful interwebs. Usually, I will take some time from Wed - Fri looking on Craigslist for garage sales. I’ve even reached out to some of the sellers before asking for more details on what they have regarding video games and have had good experiences interacting with them so far. Being able to scope out a garage sale through pictures on the internet first lowers your risk of wasting your time too. This is a great way to pick up some new things for your collection.</p>
<p>The main risk you are taking when you buy games this way is regarding the game condition. There’s no way to test the game and these types of sellers don’t exactly have a return policy. Whether or not a game cartridge will play is a complete crap-shoot and no matter how long and hard you look at a disc-based game, there’s no way to know for sure if it will actually work. So far I’ve just been careful and I would say that 95% of what I have acquired through these methods have worked.</p>
<h2 id="craigslist-offerup-letgo-etc">Craigslist, OfferUp, LetGo, etc.</h2>
<p>It is easier now than ever before to buy and sell things from person to person thanks to the various types of classified style apps and sites out there now. Scouring these apps and sites can be a good way to add more items to your collection, but not without some caveats. Going this route will put you in the same situation as with the previously mentioned approaches where there is no guarantee your new items will function. There is also a lot of terrible pricing going on with these listings, at least in my neck of the woods. It seems as if some people think that just because they are selling something that is 30-ish years old, they can ask a ridiculously inflated price. Just like before, there is no return policy here so the idea of asking retail prices or even higher is insane.</p>
<p>My approach to using these site and apps is to look for any great deals that have been recently posted. If I see something I want I won’t hesitate to immediately call or text the seller. If the post is older then there is a chance the item is sold and the seller just hasn’t updated the listing. This is especially true if the price was right! I just ignore any listings that are even close to what I would pay in a store because the store is going to have the safety net of being able to return non-functioning items. You’ll encounter some crazy folks going this route at times so be prepared for insanity to ensue.</p>
<h2 id="ebay-not-what-it-used-to-be">eBay: Not What It Used To Be</h2>
<p>I find good deals on eBay less and less often. Prices on eBay have risen with the rise in popularity of retro collecting and gaming. If you are trying to get a good deal on a single item then try looking for newer sellers with decent ratings. If a seller has tens of thousands of ratings and is highly rated then you aren’t going to get a good price, period. What you get in return is a little more assurance that the item you purchase will be authentic, in decent condition, and will match the description. Find the sellers that have at least a hundred or so ratings and are rated well as they have yet to establish “Top Rated Seller” status, therefore, they would have a harder time selling items at the same price as those sellers.</p>
<p>The best way I’ve found to use eBay is to search for game lots. Regardless of high seller ratings, you can save more if you are spending more to buy more. Let’s say you see a lot with 10 NES games going for $60. If that seller were to take those same 10 games and sell them individually they would likely average more than $6 each and you would spend quite a bit more buying them that way. Buying in lots is a win-win because the seller can make a quick buck and get rid of a chunk of inventory while you get a decent deal.</p>
<p>Another good use of eBay is for finding and purchasing those “must have” items you crave. If you are willing to pay retail value for an item you want immediately then this is the time you look for those “Top Rated Seller” badges. Lately, I’ve been on a mission to collect every Zelda game and every variant. I have purchased a few from eBay from highly rated sellers and paid retail because it is my main focus at the moment. You can’t always find exactly what you are looking for through the discounted channels.</p>
<h2 id="goodwill-a-surprising-find">Goodwill: A Surprising Find</h2>
<p>If you have a Goodwill near you then you should check it out. I just recently became aware of the fact that you can sometimes find good retro game deals here. There are two ways to use Goodwill to add to your collection.</p>
<p>First, they have auctions on bundles of games and consoles and they can sometimes good for amazing prices! My local Goodwill does a silent auction every Saturday and it ends at 3 pm. You can bid online if you can figure out their terrible website, but I recommend going in 20-30 minutes before it ends so you can see the items in person and make your bids in person. You won’t always find great deals this way, but you will occasionally go home with a steal of a deal!</p>
<p>Goodwill also sells some items through the regular method in their stores. How they determine which retro gaming items go into auctions and which go onto shelves is beyond me, but you can sometimes score a deal on a game or two off the shelves. In my experience, they basically just cram games onto a shelf and price all of the games for a console the same price. Maybe the XBOX 360 games are $6 each and the PS2 games are $4 each. Unfortunately, this means there are a lot of craptastic titles that are overpriced. O the flip side, it also means that they have some games on the shelf that might be worth $10 or more and they aren’t asking enough. Here is where you get your small win. This approach makes sense for Goodwill because it saves them the time of trying to individually price all of these games which is an area where they probably have little to no knowledge. Go check out your local Goodwill and maybe you’ll find the steal of the century!</p>
<h2 id="buying-from-a-store">Buying From a Store</h2>
<div class="image-container">
     <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515484/gaming/game_stop.jpg" alt="Game Stop store front" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515484/gaming/game_stop.jpg')">
</div>

<p>Let’s go ahead and get this out of the way: Game Stop is not a bad place to buy used games! I know it is fashionable to hate on them, but you can make some good acquisitions there, and I’m not talking about buying new games. Buying new games and even slightly discounted used games for the current generation of consoles is something we all do at Game Stop (and I stress the use of “slightly discounted” here). The deals come when you start to look at their selection of games from the last couple of generations. You won’t often incredible savings, but you can usually grab a handful of games for a fair price if you look hard enough. An example of this is when I went to Game Stop one weekend and bought 5 Halo Games, including Halo 5 for the Xbox One, for a grand total of $25! That put me one game away from having all of the Halo games, and it was quick, easy, and relatively cheap. If you are looking to grab some cheap PS3, Xbox 360, Wii, or Wii U games, Game Stop can be a decent resource if you are willing to closely look through older their selection and ignore the games that are terribly priced.</p>
<p>There isn’t a retro game store in every city and I have lived in a few cities that don’t have one. Fortunately, I currently live somewhere with a handful of these great, locally owned stores and I visit them regularly. On a regular day, you probably won’t find a great deal at a retro store. You will, however, find cool collectibles, information on local events and conferences, like-minded people to chat with about retro games, tons of first and third party gaming accessories, and a vast selection of games and consoles that have likely been tested and are priced fairly. If you make a purchase then you can leave with the piece of mind that you can return it if the items don’t function. The return policy at my local retro store gives you 2 weeks to return anything you buy there if it doesn’t work or stops working as long as you keep the receipt. This is piece-of-mind worth paying a little extra for if you are looking to purchase something over $40 or so. I also try to watch their Twitter accounts and find out when they are having specials because you can usually walk away with a pretty good deal during those times.</p>
<h2 id="social-networking">Social Networking</h2>
<p>Admittedly, this is an area where I need improvement. I know there are Facebook groups of local retro collectors that sell and trade items regularly. My problem is that I hate most social networks with such a deep-rooted passion that I refuse to even create an account. I use Twitter occasionally, but the only real gain I’ve had from Twitter is finding out when the local retro stores are having sales. I know there are deals to be had and good information to be acquired using things like Facebook groups, I just haven’t been able to bring myself to go this route yet. If you are already using social media, then I encourage you to find these groups as it could prove to be a great way to stumble across new items for your collection.</p>
<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>
<p>When you are on the hunt for crazy good deals, it helps to have some knowledge about how things are priced. It can take quite a while to gain all of this knowledge yourself, but thankfully there is a website I recommend for reference. <a href="https://www.pricecharting.com/">Pricecharting.com</a> is a great site to visit when you’re out and about and want to know what a particular video game is worth. It is easy to use and it’s free so there is no reason you shouldn’t be using it!</p>
<p>Another thing I highly recommend is to find an app for your phone that you can use to store your complete collection. This is especially useful once your collection starts to really grow as you might find yourself thinking “do I already have this?”. You can use a plain note-taking app, Google Sheets, etc, but you should at least look at the game collection apps available on your selected phone platform (iOS or Android). I’ve used a few over the years and have recently discovered <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.hairyharri.gameye&amp;hl=en_US">GAMEYE</a> which I am loving! Regardless of how you choose to approach this, just make sure you have a complete and updated copy of your collection on your person at all times!</p>
<h2 id="maybe-this-helped">Maybe This Helped?</h2>
<p>Well, there are all of my secrets to collecting, not that any of the above is really a secret. When I first started collecting I made a lot of mistakes and I still do from time to time. Maybe this post will help some new collectors up their game or even give an idea or two to some more experience collector? Regardless, if you have a secret you would like to share or some feedback to give, feel free to leave a comment below!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I Store My Games]]></title>
            <link>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-store-my-games-collection</link>
            <guid>https://joeyg.me/blog/gaming/how-i-store-my-games-collection</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[You want to make sure your games are well protected. This is a look at how to achieve that while also making them look better on your shelves.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515484/gaming/custom_cases.jpg" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515484/gaming/custom_cases.jpg')" alt="retro games in custom cases">
</div>

<p>The biggest thing about retro game collecting that I don’t care for much is the fact that most older cartridge games don’t come with cases. On the rare occasion I find an old game with the original box, I choose to store the box on a shelf separately because I don’t want it to suffer any additional wear and tear. I’ve found a few ways to safely store my retro games that not only adds additional protection to the games while in storage but also makes my collection look nicer.</p>
<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01B1DIEUM/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B01B1DIEUM&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=0d609b7d5e4793875138c441ad8ecd02">
    <div class="image-container">
        <img border="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=US&ASIN=B01B1DIEUM&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=joeyg0e-20" >
    </div>
</a>
<img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B01B1DIEUM" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" class="image-container" />

<h2 id="universal-game-cases-to-the-rescue">Universal Game Cases to the Rescue!</h2>
<p>Thankfully, there exists a wonderful thing referred to as a universal game case. These cases will store your N64, Genesis, 32X, Super NES, and more. The basic idea is that they have an array of plastic bits inside the case that allow you to fit cartridges from different consoles in varying configurations. Most games will just fit in as expected with the exception of SNES games which fit once turned sideways.</p>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515486/gaming/modified_for_nes.jpg" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515486/gaming/modified_for_nes.jpg')" alt="universal game case modified to hold a NES cartridge">
</div>

<p>These cases aren’t without their drawbacks. First, and easily my most frustrating complaint, is that NES cartridges do not fit without modification! When I took a close look at the inside of one of these cases I quickly understood why. Basically, if the plastic pieces inside were spaced out far enough to handle NES games, then games from the other consoles would just be floating inside without any kind of restraint. I did learn from a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xXAhZ3b5iHY" target="_blank">YouTube video</a> on how to easily modify these cases to allow NES games to fit using nothing more than pliers and wire cutters. Essentially, you just cut out most of the plastic supports inside of the case. I don’t like that I have to do this every time I acquire a new NES game, but at least there is a solution.</p>
<p>Second, none of the games fit snugly and can move around when handled. This really isn’t a big deal and, again, it is a product of how these have to be designed for these things to be so “universal”. I can definitely see how a game could potentially be scratched from sliding around a little while in one of these cases. Fortunately, I don’t really handle any of my games unless it is to remove them from the case so I can play them which limits my chances of causing any damage. I feel like the protection provided by these cases from dust, moisture, and other foreign particles far outweigh the possibility of the cartridge gaining any superficial scratches.</p>
<h2 id="other-more-specialized-cases">Other, More “Specialized” Cases</h2>
<p>Have something other than an old cartridge game that you want to protect? No worries! There are several other game cases out there for games from a lot of the other consoles and they all provide about the same level of protection for your cherished games.</p>
<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0039ZY4NM/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B0039ZY4NM&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=16b2ceace6bb0c5d988a26985757eafe">
    <div class="image-container">
        <img border="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=US&ASIN=B0039ZY4NM&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=joeyg0e-20" >
    </div>
</a>
<img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B0039ZY4NM" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />

<p>Another case type that has some versatility is the replacement Nintendo DS cases. There are two slots inside of these cases: one for DS and 3DS games, and one for Game Boy Advance games. Unlike the universal game cases, games fit snugly and securely inside of these cases replicating the feel of the official cases.</p>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/modified_for_gbc.jpg" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/modified_for_gbc.jpg')" alt="DS case modified for a Game Boy Color game">
</div>

<p>Not unlike the universal game cases, these can be modified to hold different game type as well. By cutting out some small, plastic pieces you can also fit your Game Boy Color and Game Boy games in these. The fit isn’t as secure as you might like, but again this is a situation where something is probably better than nothing at all. TO learn exactly how to modify these you can check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0By130YB_Bc" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>
<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002SCAI32/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B002SCAI32&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=ae6939de9a8fc006f18fc6100e4d8972">
    <div class="image-container">
        <img border="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=US&ASIN=B002SCAI32&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=joeyg0e-20" >
    </div>
</a>
<img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B002SCAI32" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" />

<p>Most recently, I bought several UMD cases to protect some loose PSP games I acquired. These also have a nice, tight fit and do a good job of replicating the look of the official cases aside from being clear. There are options out there that are smaller and less expensive, but I feel like the full-size cases look better on a shelf and allow for better organization.</p>
<h2 id="disc-based-cases">Disc Based Cases</h2>
<p>Disc-based games have the benefit of having more standardized cases. For my Wii, Wii U, Xbox, Xbox 360, GameCube, PS2, and Saturn games I use regular old DVD cases like these: <a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00GMSSUBK/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B00GMSSUBK&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=8880864134301fd136744f67ee7aa2fc">Maxtek Standard 14mm Black Single Disc DVD Cases with Outer Clear Sleeve (25 Pack)</a><img src="//ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=joeyg0e-20&l=am2&o=1&a=B00GMSSUBK" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /> . I know you can buy tall box cases for the Saturn, but I have yet to go down this path because they are a little harder to find and a bit pricier. DVD cases do a fine job of securely holding those discs and keeping them protected from scratching.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00P36ABLE/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B00P36ABLE&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=c04504aa6312e4c97063318dc11ca3cd" target="__blank">CD jewel cases</a> also work great for some of these disc-based games as well and can be found easily and cheaply. I tend to go back and forth between CD cases and DVD cases for the Dreamcast, but my motivation there lies with the availability of what size covers I can find for the game for which I am putting into the case.</p>
<h2 id="print-some-covers-for-those-cases">Print Some Covers for Those Cases</h2>
<p>Alright, so now you have all of your loose games placed into cases to provide protection. They might look nice and tidy on your shelves, but what if I told you that you can take things to the next level by printing cover inserts? There is a fantastic, community-driven site call <a href="http://www.thecoverproject.net/" target="_blank">The Cover Project</a> where you can find printable covers for tons of old games that fit inside the various case types. Simply use the search bar at the top of the page or navigate by console name and by the first letter of a game title. Once you find the covers for your game, you usually have several options for covers of that fit different case sizes and that resemble cases from different countries. Just make sure you make the best selection to suit your needs. The Cover Project also has an active forum where you can find tons of good information and ask questions. This site is fantastic for collectors who want their collection to look as nice as possible!</p>
<p>On the rare occasion, I get a new game for which I cannot find a cover on The Cover Project. You can just make your own cover in a couple of simple steps though. I usually start by downloading a cover from The Cover Project that is the size of the case I will be using. This gives me a good template to start with since these covers are usually the perfect size and proportions. Then I use Google to find any box art I can. You can usually think of a cover as three separate things: a front, a spine, and a back. If you can at least find images for these 3 sections then you can usually cobble something decent together. I open my template image in GIMP or Photoshop then, one piece at a time, move the individual images to their rough position over the template. From here I scale them to fit the area of the template they are supposed to cover and fine-tune the positioning. Before I know it, I’m looking at an acceptable cover for my game case. If the images are from different sources then there is a chance the colors might not match up too well. A few tweaks to the colors of the layer images and my creation is complete. This process does take some familiarity with photo editing techniques, but maybe I’ll go over some of the basics in a future post.</p>
<p>Printing the covers is a simple task. I load my printer with <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00006IDS8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B00006IDS8&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=f61d68335e78e8490c02acb093d310f2" target="_blank">legal paper</a> and set the size to 100%. Once the cover is printed I simply use my trusty <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003SLAAOO/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B003SLAAOO&linkCode=as2&tag=joeyg0e-20&linkId=09e0969c1aea4cea50e7bd4be17e1ad8" target="_blank">paper cutter</a> to remove the excess paper and slide the cover into the sleeve of the case. Done and done!</p>
<div class="image-container">
  <img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/march_2019_collection.jpg" onclick="openImage('https://res.cloudinary.com/https-joeyg-me/image/upload/v1552515487/gaming/march_2019_collection.jpg')" alt="image of Joey Gauthier's game collection circa March 2019">
</div>

<p>Well, there you have it. Now you know the tricks to protecting all of your old games while improving the look of your collection at the same time. It took me a while, but now I don’t have a single loose game on my shelves. I typically try to keep extra game cases on hand too. When I come home with a new game, I usually clean it, find and print the cover, place it into a case with said cover, and find a home on my game shelves for it before I even sit down. It takes a little time and money, but knowing your collection is protected and seeing the final result makes it all worth the effort!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>